{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One holder of this position was assassinated after going to a railway station to meet Vladimir Kokovstov in retaliation for signing the Eulsa Treaty. Another holder of this position earned the nickname “Razor” while heading the military police in the Kwantung Army, and attempted suicide while awaiting trial before the Tokyo War Crimes Tribunal. For 10 points, name this government position held by Ito Hirobumi and Hideki Tojo.",
      "answer": "Prime Minister of Japan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kicking Bear added a sacred article of clothing to this movement that was possibly modeled\non the temple garments of Mormons. This movement, which wore supposedly bulletproof shirts,\nwas founded by Wodziwob and popularized by Wovoka. For 10 points, identify this religious\nand social movement of 1890s Plains Indians whose practitioners were killed at Wounded Knee.",
      "answer": "Ghost Dance"
    },
    {
      "question": "One holder of this title boasted that his descendants would rule for 10,000 generations, though\ncounting him they ruled for only two. That holder of this title followed Legalist precepts while\nburning subversive books and died after taking mercury pills in search of immortality. For 10\npoints, name this title taken by Qin Shi Huang and later used by leaders of the Han dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "emperor of China",
        "huangdi",
        "di"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The Trung Sisters are national heroes of what Southeast Asian country's resistance to\nChinese occupation?",
      "answer": "Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "question": "An epic poem in this language describes a city named Tambuka. The Kilwa sultanate ruled a coast that shares its name with this language, which Julius Nyerere championed. Due to contact with Arab slave traders in places like Zanzibar, speakers of this language derived many loanwords from Arabic. For 10 points, name this Bantu language, a lingua franca of east Africa.",
      "answer": "Swahili language"
    },
    {
      "question": "This party engaged in frequent violent clashes against the Inkatha Freedom Party, and one leader defected from this party to form the Economic Freedom Fighters. This party’s armed division, Umkhonto we Sizwe, was established in response to the Sharpeville massacre. This party first rose to power in 1994, defeating F.W. De Klerk’s National Party. Jacob Zuma is the current leader of, for ten points, what anti-apartheid party in South Africa?",
      "answer": [
        "African National Congress",
        "Umkhonto we Sizwe before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In Strasbourg in 1988, this leader proposed a non-nuclear “zone of peace” that banned Chinese immigration to his homeland. This winner of the 1989 Nobel Peace Prize currently lives in Dharamshala, India, having fled after a 1959 uprising was put down by the Chinese. This man was chosen as the 14th to hold his position at the age of 2 as the reincarnation of Thubten Gyatso. For ten points, name this exiled religious figure, the leader of Tibetan Buddhism.",
      "answer": "the 14th Dalai Lama or Jetsun Jamphel Ngawang Lobsang Yeshe Tenzin Gyatso"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man relaxed his troops by noting the presence of his soldier, Gisgo, at one of his victories. This man lost his right eye while travelling over the Apennines and the Arno to reach one of his battles, where his forces defeated the army of Gaius Flaminius. The Fabian strategy was used to delay this man’s forces, and after his victory at the Battle of Cannae he was finally defeated at the Battle of Zama by his chief rival, Scipio Africanus. For ten points, name this Carthaginian general who fought Rome during the Second Punic War.",
      "answer": "Hannibal Barca"
    },
    {
      "question": "The United Kingdom almost joined this war after its fishermen were mistaken for warships in Dogger Bank by the Baltic Fleet. This war’s aftermath led to Sergei Witte’s [VIT-uh’s] industrializtion efforts and the October Manifesto. It began inconclusively at Port Arthur, and was ended, with Theodore Roosevelt’s assistance, by the Treaty of Portsmouth. For ten points, name this 1904-05 war between countries led by Tsar Nicholas II and Emperor Meiji.",
      "answer": "Russo-Japanese War"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wesley Osmus was drowned by the losing side in this battle. Victory in this battle was made possible by the cracking of the JN-25 code, completed with a ruse regarding water purification systems. William Halsey’s illness forced Raymond Spruance to take command during this battle, in which four Japanese aircraft carriers were sunk. For ten points, name this 1942 battle near a namesake atoll, often identified as a turning point in the Pacific theater.",
      "answer": "Battle of Midway"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was hired by the Muscovy Company to find a route to Japan and China, but ice fields at Svalbard cut his journey. Members of this man’s crew on the Discovery mutinied and left him with his teenage son on a small boat in a body of water now named for him. For ten points, name this English explorer whose expeditions for the Dutch East India Company paved way for the colonization of New York, where a river is also named for him.",
      "answer": "Henry Hudson"
    },
    {
      "question": "Many holders of this profession, including the Qawasmi, operated in the Trucial States on a coast named for this profession. One holder of this profession, Hayreddin Barbarossa, later became Pasha of Algeria. Stephen Decatur was forced to burn the Philadelphia in the first of several Barbary Wars, which were fought by the United States against North African holders of this profession. For ten points, name this profession, commonly practiced in modern-day Somalia, in which individuals steal valuables from ships.",
      "answer": [
        "piracy",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The school of “subaltern studies” generally studies people originally from this continent. A refugee family that immigrated from this continent is the focus of The Spirit Catches You and You Fall Down. The principle of relative pluralism in a religion that originated on this continent is typically illustrated by the parable of the blind men and an elephant. Gayathri Spivak, the Hmong, and Jainism all originated from, for ten points, what largest continent on Earth?",
      "answer": "Asia"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Ingram served as the final leader of this movement. One side in this event coaxed the Occaneechi into attacking the Susquehannock and vandalized the Green Spring estate. This rebellion, which ended when its leader died of dysentery, was prompted by governor William Berkeley’s failure to address fears of Indian attack. Jamestown was burnt during, for ten points, what 1676 rebellion of disgruntled Virginian settlers?",
      "answer": "Nathaniel Bacon’s Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rain and this resource were mythologically provided to Wagadu by a black snake called Bida until a young man cut off its head. The “silent trade” often exchanged salt for this resource, which names an African colony that gained independence from Britain in 1957. When Mansa Musa traveled the Hajj, he distributed so much of this resource in Cairo that its prices remained depressed for many years. For ten points, name this precious metal once mined in the soil of Ghana.",
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1850s, Frederick Cumberland lost a conflict over a leadership position in this industry to Sandford Fleming. A milestone in this industry was celebrated in the town of Craigellachie. Hugh Allan received kickbacks in a scandal involving this industry, which toppled the government of John A. Macdonald. A company in this industry names the CN tower in Toronto. For ten points, name this industry that was involved in the Pacific Scandal and that completed a transcontinental connection across Canada in 1885.",
      "answer": "Canadian railroads"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these structures named for Alexander the Great is known for its red color and found near Gorgon. After the Battle of the Allia, one of these structures was built and named for Servius Tullius; that structure was surpassed by the Aurelian line, built in the 3rd century AD. For ten points, name this type of defensive structure that was built by the Qin Dynasty to guard the northern border of China.",
      "answer": [
        "walls",
        "Great Wall of Gorgon",
        "Servian Walls",
        "Aurelian Walls",
        "Great Wall of China"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The unveiling of this structure’s design led James Webb and Ross Perot to withdraw support, with Perot controversially insulting its architect as an “eggroll.” An opponent of this structure called it a “gash of shame,” as its design emulates the shape of a closed wound. Frederick Hart’s Three Soldiers overlooks this memorial, of which visitors often create crayon rubbings. Maya Lin designed, for ten points, what memorial that lists the name of servicemen who died in a Southeast Asian War?",
      "answer": [
        "Vietnam Veterans Memorial",
        "descriptions of the Vietnam War memorial",
        "descriptions of the Vietnam Wall"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The remnants of this government established the Republic of Ezo after losing the Boshin War. Two and a half centuries earlier, this government was founded after its leader won the Battle of Sekigahara against the Toyotomi clan. This government’s policy of sakoku came to an end when Matthew Perry’s Black Ships forced the opening of Japan through the 1854 Convention of Kanagawa. For ten points, name this last Japanese shogunate.",
      "answer": "Tokugawa Shogunate or Tokugawa Bakufu"
    },
    {
      "question": "Anna Chennault arranged a meeting for this man with Ambassador Bui Diem that violated the Logan Act. Charles Colson admitted this man had told him that a typewriter was fabricated in the Alger Hiss case. This politician sabotaged peace talks in Vietnam in the aforementioned Chennault affair, promising better results after this man defeated Hubert Humphrey in the 1968 election. For ten points, name this US President who withdrew the US from Vietnam in 1973.",
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The construction of this location at Mount Li was described by Sima Qian [chee-ahn], who noted that streams of mercury flowed through it in an attempt to recreate the Yangtze and Yellow Rivers. This location was first discovered by workers digging a well in Xiyang [shee-yahng]. To serve their master in the afterlife, thousands of terracotta warriors were placed in, for ten points, what resting place of the first emperor of unified China?",
      "answer": [
        "The Mausoleum of the First Qin Emperor",
        "descriptions of Qin Shi Huangdi’s mausoleum",
        "Qin Shi Huangdi in place of “Qin",
        "”",
        "equivalents for mausoleum, such as tomb, burial ground, grave, etc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Duringthiswar,agroupofsoldiersunderThomasWheelerwereambushedandbesiegedatBrookfield. This war erupted after a group of men were hung for their supposed role in the murder of John Sassamon. The Great Swamp Fight occurred in this war, during which one side was led by the chieftain Metacomet. The Wampanoag fought against colonists in New England in, for ten points, what 17th century war named after a royal moniker? ANSWER:King Philip’sWar(acceptFirst IndianWar;acceptMetacomet’sWarbefore“Metacomet” is read; accept rebellion and other equivalent terms for war) (6) One of these animals is shown carried on someone’s shoulders in the Catacombs of Priscilla. The bottom-central panel of a Van Eyck work shows one of these animals circled by angels and bleeding into a goblet, known as the Adoration of a Mystic one of these animals. This animal symbolizes Jesus’ sacrifice in the Ghent Altarpiece’s depiction of the Agnus Dei. For ten points, name this herd animal that is often shown in artistic depictions of the Good Shepherd.",
      "answer": [
        "lambs or sheep",
        "Agnus Dei before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rose to power with the support of the general Mucianus, who later encouraged this man to implement a tax on urinals. This ruler sent Agricola to govern Britain and extend Roman rule into Caledonia. This ruler was campaigning in Jerusalem when he learned of Vitellius’ ambitions to become emperor, prompting this man to return to Rome and end the Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this man who founded the Flavian dynasty after the death of Nero.",
      "answer": "Vespasian or Titus Flavius Caesar Vespasianus Augustus, but do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s promotion of pro-feminist policies was noted with the statement “Women hold up half the sky.” This man began the Anti-Rightist Campaign after severe criticism led him to undo the Hundred Flowers Movement. In a failed attempt to modernize, this man encouraged peasants to create backyard furnaces during the Great Leap Forward, which began in 1958. For ten points, name this Communist chairman of China.",
      "answer": "Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
      "question": "This site was allegedly built in a single night to serve as housing for Ket Mealea. A new capital was established at the Bayon after this site was sacked by the Cham people. Completed by Jayavarman VII, this site was constructed to resemble India’s Mount Meru. This site was dedicated to Vishnu, but it was later converted into a Buddhist temple. A national flag depicts, for ten points, what Cambodian temple complex?",
      "answer": "Angkor Wat"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician sent Robert Napier to rescue missionaries from Tewodros II in the punitive expedition to Abyssinia. Lionel de Rothschild loaned this man money to finance the purchase of the Suez Canal. This man authorized the Royal Titles act to name Queen Victoria as Empress of India and served as the only Jewish prime minister to date. For ten points, name this Conservative prime minister who rivaled William Gladstone in 19th century England.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
    },
    {
      "question": "Note: two answers required. At an embassy owned by one of these countries in the other country, an indoor soccer game was interrupted by commandos setting off a bomb under the floor, beginning Operation Chavin de Huantar. That raid ended a hostage crisis that began on the 63rd birthday of the emperor of one of these two countries; the hostages were taken by members of the Tupac Amaru terrorist group, which was based in the other country. A corrupt politician who was the first man of Asian descent to become President of a non-Asian country is a citizen of these two countries. For ten points, name this pair of countries that fought an extradition battle over Alberto Fujimori.",
      "answer": [
        "Japan and Peru",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The rituals of Annaprashana and Mamabhat involve feeding rice to these people. In Japan, the holiday 7-5-3 involves giving these people haircuts. While teaching, Jesus said to bring these people to him and compared them to the ideal kind of faith. A group led by Thomas Muntzer argued against baptizing these people and was known as the Anabaptists. Naming ceremonies are held in honor of, for ten points, what type of people, one of whom is placed in a manger for Christian nativity scenes?",
      "answer": [
        "children",
        "equivalents",
        "infant",
        "baby"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this period, a diplomatic snub toward the ruling government led to the Seikanron debate over a potential invasion of Korea. The Charter Oath laid out the ideals of this period, which proved to be unacceptable to a Satsuma-based group of warriors due to provisions abolishing the practice of feudalism. For ten points, name this period following the Tokugawa Shogunate that featured Western modernizations under a namesake emperor of Japan.",
      "answer": [
        "Meiji Restoration",
        "Meiji Era"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A commander in this battle claimed that out of control Ho-Chunk allies started the attack. Despite being shot in the head and both thighs in this battle, Spier Spencer continued to command his Yellow Jackets. The victorious general in this battle succeeded in destroying Prophetstown and, twenty-nine years later, used his fame from this battle to win the Election of 1840. Shawnee forces were defeated in Indiana in, for ten points, what 1811 battle that gave William Henry Harrison a nickname used in his campaign with “Tyler, too”?",
      "answer": "Battle of Tippecanoe"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event, which may have been started by an attack by Janibeg, re-occurred in the 1850s in China and India, and again in San Francisco in 1900. The Italian city of Pistoia went into isolation during this event, which was marked by the emergence of doctors wearing bird beaks stuffed with sweet smelling flowers. At the time, this event was commonly blamed on Jews poisoning wells, but its true cause was infected fleas. For ten points, name this plague that killed a third of Europe in the 14th century.",
      "answer": [
        "Black Death",
        "Bubonic Plague",
        "the Black Plague"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first restrictive regulation on this action was the Page Act, whose intent was reversed sixty years later by the Magnuson Act. This action was carried out through the McCorkell Line during the Irish Potato Famine. A “gentleman’s agreement” under Teddy Roosevelt limited this action from Japan. Many people who performed this action were processed at Angel and Ellis Islands. For ten points, name this action that increases the population of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "immigration to the United States",
        "answers that indicate any country of origin, even though China, Ireland, and/or Japan are the only ones clued"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A 1951 song about the “Black Strap” type of this substance, performed by Groucho Marx and three others, extolled its supposed health benefits. One of George Washington’s notebooks contains a recipe for “small beer” made with this substance. A different beverage made from this liquid was supposedly invented in Nevis in the 17th century and was used to pay guards as part of the African slave trade. In 1919, 21 people were killed by a flood of, for ten points, what syrupy byproduct of sugar production, the principal ingredient in rum?",
      "answer": "Molasses or Black Treacle"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man dropped out of Reed College, he traveled India studying Zen Buddhism and seeking enlightenment. Joanna Hoffman helped market many of this man's products, one of which was named Lisa, and his employees included Andy Hertzfeld, who later founded General Magic. The mouse-driven gui [[GOO-EE]] of computers was taken over from Xerox by this man's company. Steve Wozniak and this man pioneered the personal computer revolution, producing Macintosh products. For ten points, name this co- founder of Apple, Inc.",
      "answer": "Steve Jobs"
    },
    {
      "question": "This proposal came out of a series of meetings with several Barnburners like Preston King and Hannibal Hamlin. Voting on this proposal immediately followed a proposal by Indiana Democrat William A. Wick to simply extend the line of the Missouri Compromise. Attached as a rider to a two million dollar appropriations bill to end the Mexican-American War, for ten points, what was this unsuccessful 1846 proposal by a Pennsylvania Democrat to ban slavery in the newly won territories?",
      "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
    },
    {
      "question": "This general allied with Benito Juarez to battle the forces of Emperor Maximilian, eventually deposing and succeeding Sebastian Lerdo in his highest office. Factional strife between General Bernardo Reyes and the cientificos boiled over when this man declared himself winner of the presidency for the eighth time, after which he was the target of an uprising by Francisco Madero. For ten points, name this Mexican president immediately prior to the Mexican Revolution.",
      "answer": "Porfirio Díaz or José de la Cruz Porfirio Díaz Mori"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rebellions near Hanguguan led this dynasty's \"Gentleman of the Palace,\" Zhao Gao, to lead a coup to assassinate the emperor. Shang Yang's philosophy of Legalism was the primary ideology of this dynasty, which ended the Warring States period. The first emperor of this dynasty died from an \"Elixir of Immortality\" and was responsible for the terracotta army in Xi'an. For ten points, name this short-lived dynasty from which the western name for China is derived.",
      "answer": [
        "Qin ] Dynasty",
        "Chin Dynasty"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A park in an old capital of this nation kept a herd of inviolable sacred deer. Cord-marked pottery was a hallmark of its Stone Age Jomon culture. This modern-day country made tombs called kofun during an era when it began importing Chinese culture and received Buddhist envoys from Korea. For 10 points, name this Asian nation whose Yamato clan ruled it from Nara prefecture.",
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Jomon people made midden mounds out of what natural objects, whose cowrie variety were gathered from water for use as currency in pre-colonial America?",
        "answer": "seashells"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ethnicity respected administrators called yangban under a state known in Western sources\nas the \"hermit kingdom.\" This group defeated an invasion by Toyotomi Hideyoshi at Noryang.\nFrom 1910 to 1945, Japan occupied this group's land after deposing the Joseon dynasty. For 10\npoints, name this Asian ethnicity which now lives on a divided peninsula northeast of China.",
        "answer": [
          "Koreans",
          "Hanguk-im",
          "Hanguk"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Korea rebuffed Hideyoshi using what large ships with covered hulls, which could blow\nsmoke out of a decorative dragon head at the prow?",
        "answer": [
          "turtle ships",
          "gobukseon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During Japanese occupation of this city, its Chinese inhabitants were targeted by the Sook Ching massacre. After pleading guilty to vandalizing cars, American teenager Michael P. Fay was sentenced to caning in this city. It was nicknamed the “Gibraltar of the East” under British rule, which had begun under the leadership of Stamford Raffles. Lee Kwan Yew was the “Father” of, for ten points, what Southeast Asian city-state?",
        "answer": "Republic of Singapore"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Singapore was part of this Southeast Asian nation for two years, until it expelled Singapore in 1965.",
        "answer": "Malaysia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Catonsville Nine were Catholic activists who protested this war. The case Tinker v. Des Moines protected students’ rights to protest against this war in schools. Napalm was heavily used in aerial offensives during this war, which saw large use of Agent Orange to destroy foliage. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian war won in 1975 by a Communist country once led by Ho Chi Minh.",
        "answer": "Vietnam War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "”Big-belly” modifications to these American bombers during the Vietnam War allowed them to perform carpet bombings.",
        "answer": [
          "Boeing B-52 Stratofortress",
          "either"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was defeated militarily during the fifth encirclement campaign. Otto Braun was outmaneuvered by this political leader. After a colleague was killed in a plane crash over Mongolia in 1971, it was rumored that this leader had him killed. The “Gang of Four” briefly took control after this ruler’s death. Chief foreign minister Zhou Enlai served under, for ten points, what first Chairman of the Communist Party of China?",
        "answer": "Mao Zedong"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mao’s 1935 Long March featured a trek across one of these features named for Luding. Another of these structures was under construction to connect Bangkok and Rangoon in a movie set during World War II.",
        "answer": "bridge Luding Bridge and/or Bridge Over the River Kwai"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Gay survived this battle, the only member of Torpedo Squadron Eight to do so. Dauntless dive bombers were used at this battle, in which the Mikuma and Akagi were lost. The naval code JN-25 was broken shortly before this battle, in which the Hornet and Enterprise provided air support. The Yorktown and four Japanese carriers were sunk in, for ten points, what 1942 battle, considered to be the turning point in the Pacific theater of World War II?",
        "answer": "Battle of Midway"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This admiral was the Japanese commander at Midway and had earlier planned the Pearl Harbor attacks. Less than a year after Midway, this man was killed when his plane was shot down in Operation Vengeance.",
        "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, 15,000 soldiers deliberately slowed their pace to capture a castle garrisoned by only 500 troops, thus securing victory for a clan in a 1600 battle. The motto “enrich the country, strengthen the military” was used by a government in this nation to promote industrialization; that government put down the Satsuma Rebellion. For ten points, name this imperial Asian nation which underwent the Meiji Restoration.",
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This class of samurai warriors lacked a lord or master during Japan’s feudal period. 47 of these figures notoriously avenged the death of their master in the 18th century.",
        "answer": "ronin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One emperor of this dynasty, the Jingtai Emperor, succeeded an older brother who was captured during the Tumu Crisis. This dynasty’s rise to power was cemented at the Battle of Lake Poyang, one of the largest naval battles in history. Architectural projects undertaken during this dynasty included the Porcelain Tower of Nanjing and the fortification of the Great Wall of China. During this dynasty, the Muslim eunuch Zheng He led massive voyages throughout the Indian Ocean. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty preceded by the Mongol Yuan and succeeded by the Manchu Qing.",
        "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ming Dynasty was founded by this man, a peasant who led forces against the Yuan in the Red Turban Rebellion and established the capital at Nanjing.",
        "answer": "Hongwu Emperor or Zhu Yuanzhang"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s son Fu Su was forced to commit suicide over his support for general Meng Tian. Under the advice of chancellor Li Si, this man implemented increasingly Legalist policies. This man burned the books of Confucian scholars and buried them alive to eliminate dissent. To prepare for the afterlife, this man adorned his tomb with thousands of terracotta warriors. For ten points, name this first emperor of a unified China.",
        "answer": [
          "Qin Shi Huangdi",
          "Ying Zheng",
          "Zhao Zheng",
          "King Zheng of Qin"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Qin Shi Huangdi oversaw the construction of one of these engineering projects known as Lingqu. A “Grand” one of these projects connects Beijing and Hangzhou.",
        "answer": "canals"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man led a group of Austrasians against Chilperic and Ragenfrid at the Battle of Vincy. This man was imprisoned by his rival Plectrude and fought with her for Austrasia. He came to the aid of Odo of Aquitaine in a battle where he arranged his army, entirely made up of infantry, into a square to defeat the Umayyad cavalry. For ten points, name this Frankish “Mayor of the Palace” who won the Battle of Tours, preventing an Islamic advance into Gaul, and who was the grandfather of Charlemagne.",
        "answer": "Charles Martel or Charles the Hammer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Umayyad general and governor of Cordoba was defeated and killed at the Battle of Tours.",
        "answer": "Abd al-Rahman or Abdul Rahman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people allegedly saluted Mount Kaimon and dropped flowers as they departed. An instruction manual designed for these people commanded them to shout “hissatsu” in their final moments and look for a point of entry between a smoke stack and a bridge. The term “typhoon of steel” was applied to the Battle of Okinawa due to the prevalence of Mitsubishi Zeros piloted by, for ten points, what Japanese pilots who carried out suicide attacks?",
        "answer": [
          "kamikaze pilots",
          "Tokubetsu Kogekitai"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Centuries earlier, the term “kamikaze” was used to describe the typhoons that prevented this grandson of Genghis Khan from invading the Japanese islands.",
        "answer": "Kublai Khan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician’s chosen successor died in a stunt plane crash over his office in June 1980. This politician, who implemented a program of forced sterilizations, was eventually succeeded by a man who was assassinated in 1991 by the Tamil Tigers. After this politician authorized Operation Blue Star, her own Sikh bodyguards assassinated her in 1984. For ten points, name this first female Prime Minister of India.",
        "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Indira Gandhi’s oldest son died in the 1980 plane crash, and her second son became Prime Minister in 1984 and was killed in 1991. Name either son.",
        "answer": "Sanjay Gandhi and/or Rajiv Gandhi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A politician with this last name used “unparliamentary language” while addressing John Lundrigan in the House of Commons in what became known as the “Fuddle Duddle” incident. Photos of another politician with this last name wearing blackface at an Arabian Nights gala surfaced in September of 2019; that politician’s party lost their majority in 2019 elections. For ten points, give this last name of Pierre and Justin, a father-son pair of Canadian Prime Ministers.",
        "answer": [
          "Trudeau",
          "Pierre and/or Justin Trudeau"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both Trudeaus led this Canadian political party, which introduced universal healthcare in the late 1960s. This party lost its majority in the House of Commons to the Conservative Party in 2019.",
        "answer": "Liberal Party"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Seeichi Kito and Donald Jung are among those who claim to have created these items. The largest manufacturer of these items, headquartered in Brooklyn, creates more than 4.5 million of them per day. That company, Wonton Food, unsuccessfully attempted to market these items in China. First served in the United States at the Japanese Tea Garden in San Francisco, for ten points, name these items made from flour, sugar, and vanilla, typically containing a memorable expression or a potential future event on a slip of paper.",
        "answer": "Fortune cookie"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ubiquitous paper take-out box found in US Chinese restaurants is named for this bivalve mollusk as the boxes were used by fisherman in the early-20th century. Jonathan Swift said, \"He was a bold man who first ate\" one of these creatures.",
        "answer": "Oyster"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After bombs planted by a terrorist cell ignited in this province’s CN Railway, John Diefenbaker asked “Is this Ireland?” while on national television. This province successfully transitioned from Roman Catholic run health institutions to public healthcare during its “Quiet Revolution.” Only used during the World Wars, one Prime Minister revived the War Measures Act in this Canadian province during the 1970s October Crisis. For ten points, name this Francophone Canadian province with the city of Montreal.",
        "answer": "Quebec"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When asked by the media what he would do to end the October Crisis in Quebec, this Canadian PM said “Just Watch Me.” He is the father of the current Canadian Prime Minister.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Eastern bishops met when this man called the Second Council of Constantinople which condemned the idea that Mary was the Mother of God. This man closed the Neoplatonic Academy and abolished the worship of Amun. The first plague pandemic is named for this man, and two monks smuggled silkworms from Central Asia back to this man's empire. Under this man, Isidore of Miletus and Anthemius of Tralles had the Hagia Sofia constructed. This emperor faced the Nika riots and was married to Empress Theodora. For ten points, name this Byzantine Emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Justinian I",
          "Justinian the Great"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Nika Riots stemmed from disagreements among four factions that grew up in Constantinople, all wearing different colors and supporting different teams in which sport?",
        "answer": "Chariot racing"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Explorer Henri Mouhot [[moo-HOH]] was the first westerner to discover this site while serving as a missionary in Battambang, and he claimed it was a temple which \"rivalled Solomon's.\" This site, a representation of Mount Meru, was built by Suryavarman II [[soor- yah-VAHR-mahn the second]] under the influence of Chola advisors from the Indian subcontinent. The Khmer [[KMARE]] Empire built, for ten points, what palatial complex seen on the modern flag of Cambodia?",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Angkor Wat was damaged during a firefight between Pol Pot's Khmer Rouge and an invading force from this country, which was led by the recently victorious Ho Chi Minh.",
        "answer": [
          "Vietnam",
          "Socialist Republic of Vietnam",
          "Democratic Republic of Vietnam",
          "North Vietnam"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An emperor of this dynasty established the Four Commanderies in Korea, the only successful Chinese occupation of the peninsula. This dynasty's dominance of Vietnam was temporarily undermined by the Trung Sisters' rebellion. This dynasty was briefly interrupted by the Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty of Wang Mang. This dynasty's collapse led to the Three Kingdoms period. For ten points, name this ancient Chinese dynasty that shares its name with the country's majority ethnic group.",
        "answer": "Han Dynasty or Hàncháo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wang Mang, whose brief reign ended in abject chaos, was a scholar of this Ancient Chinese philosopher, whose principles he hoped to impose on Chinese society.",
        "answer": [
          "Confucius",
          "Confucian",
          "Kong Fuzi",
          "or Kongzi",
          "or Master Kong 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's first president, Guadalupe Victoria, was among only a few of its early leaders to complete a full term. One president of this nation engineered an eighth term as president in 1910, leading to his overthrow by Francisco Madero and a ten-year civil war. Benito Juárez [[HWAH-rehz]] governed this country, but was overthrown by an Austrian archduke. Emperor Maximilian was executed after failing to conquer, for ten points, what country where Cinco de Mayo commemorates a victory over France?",
        "answer": [
          "Mexico",
          "United Mexican States, Mexican Empire,",
          "Estados Unidos Mexicanos"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The First French Intervention in Mexico is nicknamed for what type of baked confectionary? A chef of this specific type of food complained to the French government after Mexican soldiers looted his shop, leading to the intervention.",
        "answer": [
          "Pastry or Pastries",
          "Pastry War",
          "or Guerra de los pasteles",
          "or Guerre des Pâtisseries"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group intentionally sparked the Regina [[ruh-JY-nah]] Riots in an attempt to crush a mass protest of unemployed men. This group was able to successfully infiltrate the Communist Party of its nation, and one of this group's most notable accomplishments was capturing stagecoach robber Bill Miner. The nickname of this group derives from their now- defunct standard of riding horses. For ten points, name this police force that is responsible for civil control in Canada.",
        "answer": [
          "Mounties",
          "Royal Canadian Mounted Police",
          "RCMP"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Regina Riots of 1935 effectively ended this \"trek\" of unemployed men known as \"On-to-[this Ontario city].\"",
        "answer": "Ottawa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The oldest-known evidence of this kind of event was found on a three thousand- year old Japanese skeleton discovered in 2021. A number of these incidents occurred on the Jersey Shore in 1916, and, after being torpedoed by the Japanese in 1945, the survivors of the USS Indianapolis dealt with hundreds of these incidents while waiting for rescue. For ten points, name these historically-feared events in which a large cartilaginous [[kar-tih-LAH- jih-nus]] fish injures or kills a human.",
        "answer": [
          "Shark attack or Shark bite",
          "descriptive answers involving humans being attacked and/or injured by sharks"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the past decade, the waters off which U.S. East Coast landmass have been the site of extremely dense white shark concentrations, leading to five attacks since 2012? Bartholemew Gosnold led the first English expedition to this landmass and coined its name in 1602.",
        "answer": "Cape Cod 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the first of these wars, bureaucratic corruption led to wrong caliber shells being outfitted on Admiral Ding Ruchang's ships, resulting in his loss at the Battle of Yalu River. The Treaty of Shimonoseki ended the first of these wars, giving one power hegemony over Korea. The second of these wars began after the Marco Polo Bridge Incident occurred outside Beijing. For ten points, give this name of two wars between two East Asian superpowers, the first fought between the Qing and the Meiji governments.",
        "answer": "Sino-Japanese War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Shimonoseki gave Japan a \"most favored nation status\" in terms of trade with China. It was later dubbed one of these one-sided agreements the Qing signed with various Western powers.",
        "answer": "Unequal Treaties or Bùpíngděng Tiáoyuē"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "BREAKAWAY REGIONS",
      "prompt": "Who or what is or was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Oil-rich African country with capital at Abuja which Biafra broke away from?",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central Asian nation which has breakaway regions in Abkhazia and South Ossetia and shares\nits name with a U.S. sate?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Catalan separatists have been protesting in Barcelona?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Middle East ethnic group who have tried to break off from Turkey and have autonomy within\nIraq?",
          "answer": [
            "Kurds",
            "Kurdish"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country targeted by the Western Sahara independence movement?",
          "answer": "Morocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian country which seized Goa from the Portuguese?",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "French-speaking West African country where Azawad tried to secede in 2012?",
          "answer": "Mali"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disputed region fought over by Armenia and Azerbaijan in a 1991 war?",
          "answer": "Nagorno-Karabakh"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "7. League of Lutheran Princes opposed Emperor Charles V?",
      "prompt": "Who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The colonial power that ruled Indonesia until its independence in 1950?",
          "answer": "the Netherlands"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proponent of “Guided Democracy” who served as the first President?",
          "answer": "Sukarno"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who ruled Indonesia until the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis?",
          "answer": "Suharto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Now-independent former Portuguese colony occupied by Indonesia until 1999?",
          "answer": "East Timor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighboring nation that fought against Indonesia in the Konfrontasi?",
          "answer": "Malaysia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city, formerly known as Batavia, that has served as its capital since independence?",
          "answer": "Jakarta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Special region on the north of Sumatra hit hardest by the 2004 Indian Ocean tsunami?",
          "answer": "Aceh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Militant Islamic terrorist group that carried out the 2002 Bali bombings?",
          "answer": "Jemaah Islamiah"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "history. Name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the history. name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. President and Rough Rider who wrote that phrase in his diary in 1884.",
          "answer": "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only other letter used by Roosevelt in that diary entry.",
          "answer": "X"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-violent Indian independence leader who was assassinated in 1948.",
          "answer": "Mohandas or Mahatma Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in which that assassination took place, the capital of India.",
          "answer": "New Delhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian Prime Minister whose speech to the country after that assassination used the phrase.",
          "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        },
        {
          "question": "Latin-derived term that describes that speech, as it was delivered with no preparation.",
          "answer": [
            "extemperaneous or word forms",
            "ex tempore",
            "impromptu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Hindu nationalist who carried out the assassination in India.",
          "answer": "Nathuram Vinayak Godse"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Earl, later killed in his fishing boat by the IRA, who encouraged the Prime Minister to give the speech.",
          "answer": "Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mexican Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country that sent the Zimmermann Telegram to Mexico during the revolution, trying to trigger an invasion of the US.",
          "answer": "Germany"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. president who intervened by occupying Veracruz and led the US during World War I.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artist of Man at the Crossroads who supported the revolution with his murals.",
          "answer": "Diego Rivera"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party founded after the Revolution, which dominated Mexican politics for much of the 20th century.",
          "answer": [
            "PRI or Partido Revolucionario Institucional",
            "Institutional Revolutionary Party"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who led a peasant revolution in Morelos, authored the Plan of Ayala, and inspired an agrarian movement.",
          "answer": [
            "Emiliano Zapata",
            "Zapatistas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime dictator of Mexico overthrown during the revolution.",
          "answer": "Porfirio D´ıaz"
        },
        {
          "question": "The man who led the initial revolution with the Plan of San Luis Potos´ı. He became president after the Treaty of Ciudad Ju´arez.",
          "answer": "Francisco Madero"
        },
        {
          "question": "General that launched the Ten Tragic Days coup to become President of Mexico.",
          "answer": "Victoriano Huerta"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Non-Aligned Movement",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Only African country that is not a member, having gained its independence in 2011.",
          "answer": "South Sudan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current Secretary General of the NAM, the President of Venezuela.",
          "answer": "Nicolas Maduro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Previous Secretary General of the NAM, the President of Iran.",
          "answer": "Hassan Rouhani"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only remaining European country in the NAM, led by Alexander Lukashenko.",
          "answer": "Belarus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that hosted the 1970 NAM conference in Lusaka under Secretary General Kenneth Kaunda.",
          "answer": "Zambia"
        },
        {
          "question": "1955 conference in Indonesia that inspired the founding of the NAM.",
          "answer": "Bandung Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of North Vietnam, the namesake of Vietnam’s largest city, who attended that conference.",
          "answer": [
            "Ho Chi Minh",
            "Ho Chi Minh City"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese premier who survived an assassination attempt en route to that conference.",
          "answer": "Zhou Enlai"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "British Canada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Neighbor country whose Articles of Confederation allowed for the annexation of British Canada.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "USA",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "European rival country from whom Britain took Canada in the 1763 Treaty of Paris.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of France"
        },
        {
          "question": "War ended by the aforementioned 1763 Treaty of Paris.",
          "answer": [
            "Seven Years’ War",
            "French and Indian War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Collection of former British colonies, including Canada and Australia, led ceremonially by Queen Elizabeth.",
          "answer": "Commonwealth of Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern city fought over in the Battle of the Plains of Abraham.",
          "answer": "Quebec City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity whose trade was fought over by the Hudson’s Bay Company and coureurs de bois [coo-ror de bwa].",
          "answer": [
            "furs",
            "fur trade, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First Canadian Prime Minister, who took power after Britain granted semi-independence to Canada.",
          "answer": "John Alexander Macdonald"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who led the 1837 Upper Canada Rebellion, or the later Canadian Prime Minister named after this man who feuded with Lord Byng.",
          "answer": "William Lyon Mackenzie and/or William Lyon Mackenzie King"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Dutch East India Company",
      "prompt": "Name the dutch east india company...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Dutch capital city where it was incorporated.",
          "answer": "Amsterdam"
        },
        {
          "question": "City built by the VOC over the ruins of Jakarta in 1620, becoming the VOC’s Indonesian capital.",
          "answer": "Batavia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Form of torture, a simulation of drowning, committed by VOC men before the murders in the Amboyna Massacre.",
          "answer": "waterboarding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Southeast Asian country where the VOC traded with the Ayutthaya Kingdom.",
          "answer": [
            "Thailand",
            "Siam"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Southeast Asian country where the VOC intervened in the Trinh-Nguyen War.",
          "answer": "Vietnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where the VOC was forced out by the Koxinga [ko-shin-ga] in 1662.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiwan",
            "Formosa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Artificial island off Nagasaki from which the VOC traded with the Japanese for over 200 years.",
          "answer": "Dejima Island"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indonesian sultanate whose gold trade was taken by the VOC with the Painan Treaty.",
          "answer": "Aceh Sultanate"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Brazil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country that colonized Brazil, and whose language is Brazil’s official language.",
          "answer": [
            "Portugal",
            "Portuguese"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Site of the 2016 Summer Olympics, the second largest Brazilian city after Sao Paulo.",
          "answer": "Rio de Janeiro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Beverage whose industry dominated the 19th century Brazilian economy, often paired with milk in historical studies.",
          "answer": [
            "coffee",
            "coffee with milk",
            "caf’e com leite"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that opposed Brazil, Argentina, and Uruguay in the War of the Triple Alliance.",
          "answer": "Paraguay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Practice that was abolished in Brazil by the 1888 Golden Law.",
          "answer": "slavery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor of Brazil whose daughter Isabel signed the Golden Law while serving as regent.",
          "answer": "Dom Pedro II"
        },
        {
          "question": "President from 1956 to 1961 who built the new capital at Brasilia.",
          "answer": "Juscelino Kubitschek de Oliveira"
        },
        {
          "question": "River where, in 1822, the “cry” of Brazilian independence was made.",
          "answer": [
            "Ipiranga Brook",
            "Cry of Ipiranga"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Decline of Imperial China",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Final dynasty of China.",
          "answer": "Qing Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Century in which that dynasty fell during the Xinhai [shin-hi] Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "20th century",
            "1900s"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City where the final Emperor of China resided in the Forbidden City.",
          "answer": [
            "Beijing",
            "Peking"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellion started by the Righteous and Harmonious Fists that led to foreign domination over China.",
          "answer": [
            "Boxer Rebellion",
            "Yihetuan Movement",
            "Quan Luan Rebellion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "General and mentor to Chiang Kai-Shek who organized several post-Imperial governments.",
          "answer": [
            "Sun Yat-sen",
            "Sun Zhongsha"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Empress Dowager who led a coup against the Hundred Days’ Reform.",
          "answer": [
            "Empress Dowager Cixi",
            "Empress Xiaoqinxian",
            "Xingzhen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Last official imperial ruler of China; he was later installed by the Japanese as Emperor of Manchukuo.",
          "answer": [
            "Puyi",
            "Xuantong Emperor",
            "Kangde Emperor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Government official who assumed the name Hongxian [hong-shee-ahn] Emperor in a short-lived bid for power.",
          "answer": "Yuan Shikai"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Recent Asian Economic History",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that became one of the “Four Asian Tigers” through tech companies like Samsung and LG.",
          "answer": "South Korea"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Tiger” that built a new financial center, Taipei 101, in 2004.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiwan",
            "Republic of China"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President of China who has implemented market reforms since 2012.",
          "answer": "Xi Jinping"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where an asset price bubble ushered in the Lost Decade in the early 90s.",
          "answer": [
            "Japan",
            "Nippon",
            "Nihon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Multi-national organization based in Jakarta that was created by the Bangkok Declaration.",
          "answer": "ASEAN"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Indonesia, the successor of Sukarno, who was removed by riots stemming from an financial crisis.",
          "answer": "Suharto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which that massive financial crisis began.",
          "answer": "1997"
        },
        {
          "question": "Currency whose collapse kicked off that financial crisis after it could no longer stay pegged to the dollar.",
          "answer": "Thai baht"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Activism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Square in Beijing where democratic activists protested and were crushed by tanks in 1989.",
          "answer": "Tiananmen Square"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home country of Nobel laureate Kim Dae-jung, who was targeted for assassination by dictator Park Chung-hee in 1973.",
          "answer": [
            "South Korea or Republic of Korea",
            "ROK"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Home country of Nobel laureate Mohamed ElBaradei, who briefly became Vice President after a coup against Mohamed Morsi.",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Electrician who led the Solidarity trade union against Communist rule and became President of Poland.",
          "answer": "Lech Walesa"
        },
        {
          "question": "South African archbishop who won a Nobel Peace Prize for fighting apartheid.",
          "answer": "Desmond Tutu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where author Ken Saro-Wiwa and the Ogoni Nine were hanged by Sani Abacha’s forces.",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nobel laureate who was imprisoned after signing the Charter 08 manifesto.",
          "answer": "Liu Xiaobo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Venezuelan leader whose namesake doctrine is a refusal to recognize governments that come to power by force.",
          "answer": "Romulo Betancourt"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Chinese Unrest",
      "prompt": "Name the Chinese rebellion that was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Supported by the Qing Dynasty, and was defeated by the western Eight-Nation Alliance in 1901.",
          "answer": [
            "Boxer Rebellion",
            "Yihetuan Movement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by a supposed brother of Jesus named Hong Xiuquan and established a heavenly kingdom in Nanjing.",
          "answer": "Taiping Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by the Zhang family and which led to the Three Kingdoms period.",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
            "Yellow Scarves Rebellion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Carried out by followers of a hybrid Buddhism movement, named for a flower.",
          "answer": "White Lotus Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by Zhang Lu, whose adherents had to donate food to enter; they surrendered to Cao Cao [sow sow] in 215 AD.",
          "answer": [
            "Way of the Celestial Masters",
            "Way of the Five Pecks of Rice",
            "Wu dou Mi Dao"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by Zhu Yuanzhang, who eventually named himself the Hongwu Emperor, against the Yuan.",
          "answer": [
            "Red Turban Rebellion",
            "Red Scarves Rebellion",
            "Hongjin Qiyi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sparked by the Wuchang Uprising; it ended imperial rule in China in 1911.",
          "answer": "Xinhai Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by farmers against the Xin [shin] dynasty; it was named for its followers’ painting their faces to appear like demons.",
          "answer": [
            "Red Eyebrows",
            "Chimei"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Boxer Rebellion",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Religion whose missionaries were labelled as “devils” by the Boxers.",
          "answer": "Christianity"
        },
        {
          "question": "Manchurian dynasty during which the rebellion occurred.",
          "answer": "Great Qing Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital whose occupation by the Gaselee Expedition nominally ended the rebellion.",
          "answer": [
            "Beijing",
            "Peking"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian nation that defeated China in an 1895 war, setting the stage for the rebellion.",
          "answer": "Empire of Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "General name for the one-sided “Treaties” China signed with the West, including the Boxer Protocol.",
          "answer": "Unequal Treaties"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future US President trapped in China during the rebellion while working as a mining engineer.",
          "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Alliance” of countries which subdued the rebellion through military intervention.",
          "answer": "Eight-Nation Alliance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Province of China in which the rebellion began and whose city of Qingdao [[CHING- DOW]] was leased to Germany.",
          "answer": "Shandong or Shantung 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Heian Period",
      "prompt": "In the Heian Period, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Japanese national garment, a robe that evolved from the kosode.",
          "answer": "Kimono"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion that developed as the Tendai Sect in Japan, based on the Lotus Sutra.",
          "answer": [
            "Mahayana Buddhism",
            "either word"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lady Murasaki work that may be the world's first novel.",
          "answer": "The Tale of Genji"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern city that contains Heian-kyo, Japan’s capital before Tokyo.",
          "answer": "Kyoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sei Shonagon book relating her time as court lady in the Heian court.",
          "answer": "The Pillow Book"
        },
        {
          "question": "War between the Taira and Minamoto clans that ended the Heian.",
          "answer": "Genpei War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clan that held true power in the Heian period by monopolizing the sessho and kampaku and marrying daughters to Emperors.",
          "answer": "Fujiwara Clan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bifurcated system of rule that led to retirement positions like the Daijo Tenno.",
          "answer": "Cloistered Rule or Insei 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7",
      "prompt": "Concerning Indian independence, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader known as \"Mahatma.\"",
          "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi or Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "First prime minister of independent India.",
          "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru or Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru"
        },
        {
          "question": "General term for the 1947 division which separated the British Raj into Pakistan and India.",
          "answer": "Partition of India"
        },
        {
          "question": "All-India Muslim League leader who headed the independent government of Pakistan.",
          "answer": "Muhammad Ali Jinnah or Mahomedali Jinnahbhai"
        },
        {
          "question": "1930 \"March\" sometimes known as the \"Satyagraha [[sah-tyah-GRAH-hah]].\"",
          "answer": [
            "Salt march to Dandi",
            "the Dandi March"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Last British Governor-General of India who oversaw official independence.",
          "answer": "Lord Mountbatten or Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hindu term for \"self-governance,\" used synonymously with \"home-rule.\"",
          "answer": "Swaraj ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the INA who made overtures to the Axis powers in an attempt to free the subcontinent from British rule.",
          "answer": [
            "Subhas Chandra Bose",
            "Netaji 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Qing Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty of 1644 to 1912, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Massive country which it controlled.",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Empire of China",
            "Imperial China",
            "Zhōngguó"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Resource-rich region of Northeast Asia where the Qing dynasty originated.",
          "answer": [
            "Manchuria",
            "Manchu",
            "or Manchurians",
            "Dōngsānshěng",
            "or Guangdong",
            "Jurchens"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Two wars named for a narcotic, both victories for the British Empire over the Qing.",
          "answer": "Opium Wars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last native dynasty destabilized by internal rebellion and overthrown by the Qing.",
          "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last emperor of the Qing who was placed on the throne of the Japanese puppet state, Manchukuo [[MAN-CHOO-KWOH]].",
          "answer": [
            "Emperor Puyi",
            "Henry Puyi",
            "Xuantong Emperor",
            "Yaozhi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellion launched by civil servant Hong Xiuquan [[SHOO-CHWAN]], who attempted to found a Heavenly Kingdom.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiping Rebellion or Taiping Civil War",
            "or Taiping Revolution"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Dowager Empress\" who controlled the Qing government through the Hundred Days Reform and died in 1908.",
          "answer": [
            "Cixi ] or Empress Dowager Cixi",
            "or Cíxī Tàihòu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1911 Revolution that collapsed Qing rule, resulting in the disastrous rise of Yuan Shikai.",
          "answer": "Xinhai Revolution 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Kamakura Period",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Kamakura Period of Japan, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Japanese warrior nobles which first appeared during the period.",
          "answer": "Samurai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military position first held by Minamoto no Yoritomo [[mih-nah-MOH-toh noh toh- ree-TOH-moh]], making him the de facto head of Japan.",
          "answer": "Shogun"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Divine Wind,\" likely a typhoon, which sunk the Mongol navy in their attempt to conquer Japan.",
          "answer": "Kamikaze ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sect of Buddhism introduced to Japan by Dōgen [[DOH-gen]].",
          "answer": "Zen Buddhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Landless warriors whom warlords hired to supplement armies during the dynastic conflicts of the period.",
          "answer": "Rōnin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clan whose leader Takauji [[tah-kah-OO-jee]] established himself as leader of Japan in 1337.",
          "answer": [
            "Ashikaga ]",
            "Ashikaga shogunate"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Brief \"Restoration\" by Go-Daigo [[goh-\"die\"-GOH]] which overthrew the Kamakura in favor of direct imperial rule.",
          "answer": "Kenmu Restoration or Kenmu no shinsei"
        },
        {
          "question": "War between the Taira [[tah-EE-rah]] and Minamoto clans that led to the establishment of the Kamakura.",
          "answer": [
            "Genpei War ]",
            "Genpei kassen",
            "Jisho-Juei War 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This program had a complex system of over three \"work classifications\" and targeted those with educational problems; eighty-nine percent of its participants had not graduated high school. This program, directed by Robert Fechner, sent the Indian Division to work on (20 pts)",
        "soil projects. This program employed three million people and planted three (10 pts)",
        "billion trees from 1933 to 1942. For 10 points, name this New Deal program in which men lived in camps and worked outdoors."
      ],
      "answer": "CCC"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader oversaw the annexation of Sikkim by referendum. This leader’s son oversaw a mass sterilization campaign during the (20 pts)",
        "Emergency. While going to an interview with Peter Ustinov, this leader was shot by her own (10 pts)",
        "bodyguards in retaliation for ordering an attack in Amritsar. For 10 points, name this prime minister of India, the daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru."
      ],
      "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1994, this tribe launched an economic program based on the crossbreeding of the Akhal-Teke and the Appaloosa into their namesake breed of fast horse. This tribe lost the Battle of Bear Paw during an 1877 (20 pts)",
        "war named for them in which they were originally led by Looking Glass. Nelson Miles stopped this tribe's flight to Canada, which was organized by the man who said \"I will (10 pts)",
        "fight no more forever.\" For 10 points, name this American Indian tribe of Chief Joseph."
      ],
      "answer": "Nez Perce"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) David Harris's Omega organization advocated this activity. A Phil Ochs song about doing this listed flat feet and a ruptured spleen as ways to accomplish it. Nearly all people who did this were pardoned by Jimmy Carter, though accusations of doing it have since haunted (20 pts)",
        "Bill Clinton, George W. Bush, and Dick Cheney. Many people who did this temporarily (10 pts)",
        "fled to Canada. For 10 points, what was this activity which people who did not wish to fight in Vietnam performed?"
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam \"draft dodging\""
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Note to moderator: This question has a complex answer line. Please examine it for a moment before beginning to read. The territorial waters of these two countries are separated by the Northern Limit Line. The Bridge of No Return allowed passage between these two countries until 1976, when the bridge was closed following Operation (20 pts)",
        "Paul Bunyan, a response to the Axe Murder Incident. These two countries were required by a 1953 (10 pts)",
        "armistice to establish a four-kilometer buffer now known as the Demilitarized Zone. For 10 points, name these rival countries on an East Asian peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": "North Korea and South Korea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Borden accused this man of being a Soviet agent in a letter sent to J. Edgar Hoover. This friend of Richard Tolman and teacher of George Volkoff noted that stars of a certain mass could not become (20 pts)",
        "neutron stars. During the Trinity test, this scientist noted that he had (10 pts)",
        "“become Death, the destroyer of worlds,” a month before his creation was used in Japan. For ten points, name this leader of the Manhattan Project and father of the atomic bomb."
      ],
      "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who defined his philosophy in The Story of My Experiments with Truth, signed a pact with Lord Irwin before the Second Round Table Conference to discuss dominion status. This man called for the use of (20 pts)",
        "khadi, or homespun cloth, in opposition to foreign textiles, and he traveled to Dandi to violate a foreign tax during the (10 pts)",
        "Salt March. This man advocated for a form of civil disobedience called satyagraha. For ten points, name this pacifist and leader of the Indian independence movement."
      ],
      "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi or Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to a possibly apocryphal story, this man fled his home when Michael VIII Palaiologos ordered the Venetian Quarter of Constantinople burned down. After one voyage, this man was allegedly captured at the Battle of Curzola by (20 pts)",
        "Genoans. During one trek, he traveled by camel to Hormuz before arriving at Shengdu. This man’s credibility was brought into question by historians who noticed that this man never wrote about (10 pts)",
        "footbinding, walls, or chopsticks. Kublai Khan was supposedly the patron of, for ten points, what Italian merchant who traveled to the Yuan Dynasty in China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Marco Polo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Miguel de la Madrid was criticized for not allowing foreign aid after one of these events. The deadliest of these events in modern history struck Tangshan, China in 1976. The Marquis of Pombal cemented his power by rebuilding (20 pts)",
        "Lisbon after one of these events in 1755 caused widespread fires and a (10 pts)",
        "tsunami. Sixty-three people died in 1989 after one of these struck near Loma Prieta on the San Andreas fault. For ten points, name these natural disasters, one of which devastated San Francisco in 1906, that are commonly followed by deadly aftershocks."
      ],
      "answer": "earthquakes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Leaders of this nation derived their title from the phrase “tent government.” One leader of this nation won a battle through the ingenious use of arquebuses to puncture the armor of cavalry; his ally would win the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Sekigahara to take control of this nation and form a bakufu. Matthew (10 pts)",
        "Perry’s black ships forced this nation to sign a treaty with the U.S., ending its isolationism. For ten points, name this country ruled by Oda Nobunaga and Tokugawa Ieyasu."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Japan",
        "Nippon",
        "Nihon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man described his descent into alcoholism in his autobiography Magnificent Desolation. When invited for an interview supposedly for Japanese children, this man was accused on camera by Bart Sibrel of being a “coward and a liar,” so he (20 pts)",
        "punched him in the jaw. This man, who engaged in an over two-hour long spacewalk as part of Gemini 12, began another walk twenty minutes (10 pts)",
        "after the commander of the Eagle. For ten points, name this pilot of the Apollo 11 mission alongside commander Neil Armstrong."
      ],
      "answer": "Edwin Eugene “Buzz” Aldrin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The lands of these people were surveyed by Henry Bulwer, who tried to convince Bartle Frere not to begin a series of annexations. Lord Chelmsford gave these people an ultimatum in order to force them to declare war, a conflict that ended when (20 pts)",
        "Ulundi was burned and king Cetshwayo was sent into exile. These people fought the battles of (10 pts)",
        "Isandlwana and Rorke’s Drift against British forces. For ten points, name this South African ethnic group that was once led by Shaka."
      ],
      "answer": "Zulu Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This location inspired a similar development in Toa Baja, Puerto Rico that was divided into eight sections and numerous sub-sections. Zip code 11756 was given to this location, where documents required that “any person other than a member of the (20 pts)",
        "Caucasian race” could not buy. This location in Nassau County consisted of units that could be (10 pts)",
        "financed with 30-year mortgages that required no down payment. At one point, a house was built every 16 minutes in, for ten points, what “mass-produced” suburb in 1950s New York?"
      ],
      "answer": "Levittown"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Denis Kearny threatened to manufacture balloons for dropping dynamite on one of these places. People who came to one of these places after a 1906 earthquake were called “paper sons.” (20 pts)",
        "In one of these places, Doyers Street became known as “Murder Alley” due to violence among Tong gangs. Immigrants settled in one of these places in San Francisco after the repeal of an 1882 (10 pts)",
        "Exclusion Act. Paifang gates and dragon decorations are common in, for ten points, what urban neighborhoods developed by immigrants from a certain Asian country?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chinatowns",
        "Tangrenjie"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was sued by the family of Rene Schneider after this man’s order to stand down led to the kidnapping and death of Schneider. This man was replaced by Brent Scowcroft as National Security Advisor during the “Halloween (20 pts)",
        "Massacre” in Gerald Ford’s cabinet. For his role in seeking a “peace with honor,” a Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to this man and (10 pts)",
        "Le Duc Tho, who declined the award. This man negotiated with Zhou Enlai to orchestrate a visit to Mao Zedong in China. For ten points, name this man who served as Richard Nixon’s Secretary of State."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry Kissinger"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s Prime Minister was assassinated by disguised electricians during Operation Ogre. This leader, who was given command of the Army of Africa by Emilio Mola, rose to prominence during the (20 pts)",
        "Rif War in Morocco. This ruler came to power after forming a coalition of the (10 pts)",
        "Falange and Carlists to defeat the Republican faction, but he restored the monarchy before his death, leading to the ascension of Juan Carlos I. For ten points, name this fascist dictator of Spain."
      ],
      "answer": "Francisco Franco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After the 1979 overthrow of Jean-Bédel Bokassa [[zhen-BEH-dehl boh-KAH- suh]], this man became the world's only reigning \"Emperor.\" This man was almost deposed in the Kyūjō [[KYOO-joh]] incident, (20 pts)",
        "which occurred prior to the \"Jewel Voice\" broadcast. This son of Taisho, [[\"TIE\"-shoh]] and grandson of Meiji [[MEH- jee]], became the only ruler on the Chrysanthemum (10 pts)",
        "Throne to experience a foreign occupation after his country was bombed with nuclear weapons. For ten points, name this Japanese emperor during World War Two."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hirohito",
        "Shōwa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Periplus of the Erythraean [[eh-rith-REH-an]] Sea recounts how Rome traded for this commodity with the Chera Dynasty's merchants on the Malabar Coast. Zheng He's [[ZHEHNG HUHS]] voyage through the Indian (20 pts)",
        "Ocean led to this spice transforming from a luxury item to a common household product in Ming China. This spice was colloquially known as \"black gold\" in the early modern period by Europeans. Salt is (10 pts)",
        "historically paired with, for ten points, what spice?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Black Pepper",
        "Peppercorn"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people erected a namesake \"Stele\" [[STEE-lee]] in modern Xi'an [[SHEE- AHN]] written in both Chinese and Syriac. Two holy men of this faith supposedly smuggled silkworms out of China and brought them to the court of Justinian the Great. Hong (20 pts)",
        "Xiuquan [[SHU-CHWAN]], the leader of the Taiping Rebellion, claimed to be the younger brother of this faith's (10 pts)",
        "messiah. Matteo Ricci [[REE-chee]] visited China as a Jesuit missionary of, for ten points, which Abrahamic faith?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chinese Christians or Christianity",
        "Catholicism",
        "Nestorianism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "The Indian grammarian Panini developed a system of this field that bears similarities to a type created by the author of The Laws of Thought. Used in a namesake type of algebra, this branch's Boolean (*) form uses values like true and false. The syllogism was developed by Aristotle while studying this field of thought. (*) For ten points, name this philosophical field with applications in math and computer science, the informal type of which studies the validity of arguments."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Logic",
        "Boolean Logic",
        "Pramana",
        "Anviksiki",
        "Formal",
        "Informal Logic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Leather examples of these object are used in a form of theatre performed by the Kannada people to retell stories like the Ramayana. Taiko [[tah-EE-koh]] drummers and tayū chanters are used in a form of theater using these objects named (*) bunraku [[boon-RAH-koo]] native to Japan. A form of art using these figures grew in popularity in the U.S. in the vaudeville circuits of the 1800s. (*) Ventriloquism is an art form using, for ten points, what objects that usually represent people and are manipulated for theatre."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Puppets",
        "Puppet Theatre",
        "Puppettry",
        "Dolls",
        "Bunraku",
        "marionette before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The negotiation of the Suez Crisis was done by a diplomat from this political party, Lester Pearson. The Shawinigan [[shah-WEH-neh-gehn]] (20 pts)",
        "Handshake, which was a chokehold against a protestor by a leader of this party, occurred during anti- poverty protests in Gatineau [[gah-tee-NOW]], Quebec. Pierre and Justin (10 pts)",
        "Trudeau both served as leaders of, for ten points, which Canadian political party, the traditional opponents of the Conservatives?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Liberal Party of Canada",
        "Parti libéral du Canada"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This war likely led to the victory of Lord Salisbury's Conservatives in the \"Khaki Election.\" A modified Maxim gun known as the \"Pom-Pom\" was introduced during this war, and its last two years degenerated into guerilla warfare under generals like Jan [[YAHN]] (20 pts)",
        "Smuts. The sieges of Kimberly and Mafeking [[MAH- feh-king]] occurred during this war, which was named for (10 pts)",
        "Dutch settlers of Africa. The Transvaal and the Orange Free State were incorporated into South Africa following, for ten points, what turn of the twentieth century conflict?"
      ],
      "answer": "Second Boer War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Near the end of his life, this man prepared the defense of Gibraltar after it was threatened by the Castilian king Alfonso XI [[the eleventh]]. This Berber's sixteen month hajj to Mecca continued as he joined a caravan aiming to trade within the Il- khanate. The (*) travelogue known informally as The Rihla recounts this man's visit to Yuan China, the Swahili Coast, and the Indian subcontinent. (*) For ten points, name this medieval Moroccan explorer who traveled over ten times as far as Marco Polo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ibn Battuta",
        "Abu Abdullah Muhammad ibn Battuta"
      ]
    }
  ]
}